<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>DMRG cond-mat</title>
    <link>http://quattro.phys.sci.kobe-u.ac.jp/dmrg/condmat.html</link>
    <description>Aggregated feed from DMRG cond-mat page, includes abstracts and authors from arXiv (sorted by publication date, newest first)</description>
    <ns0:link href="http://quattro.phys.sci.kobe-u.ac.jp/dmrg/condmat.html" rel="self" />
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 12:15:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03832</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03832'&gt;arXiv:2601.03832&lt;/a&gt;] Published Unknown UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03832</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 12:15:17 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03885</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03885'&gt;arXiv:2601.03885&lt;/a&gt;] Published Unknown UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03885</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 12:15:17 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04172</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04172'&gt;arXiv:2601.04172&lt;/a&gt;] Published Unknown UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04172</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 12:15:17 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Full grid solution for multi-asset options pricing with tensor networks</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00009</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Lucas Arenstein, Michael Kastoryano&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Pricing multi-asset options via the Black-Scholes PDE is limited by the curse of dimensionality: classical full-grid solvers scale exponentially in the number of underlyings and are effectively restricted to three assets. Practitioners typically rely on Monte Carlo methods for computing complex instrument involving multiple correlated underlyings. We show that quantized tensor trains (QTT) turn the d-asset Black-Scholes PDE into a tractable high-dimensional problem on a personal computer. We construct QTT representations of the operator, payoffs, and boundary conditions with ranks that scale polynomially in d and polylogarithmically in the grid size, and build two solvers: a time-stepping algorithm for European and American options and a space-time algorithm for European options. We compute full-grid prices and Greeks for correlated basket and max-min options in three to five dimensions with high accuracy. The methods introduced can comfortably be pushed to full-grid solutions on 10-15 underlyings, with further algorithmic optimization and more compute power.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00009'&gt;arXiv:2601.00009&lt;/a&gt;] Published Sat, 20 Dec 2025 17:24:57 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00009</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 17:24:57 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Random-Matrix-Induced Simplicity Bias in Over-parameterized Variational Quantum Circuits</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01877</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Jun Qi, Chao-Han Huck Yang, Pin-Yu Chen, Min-Hsiu Hsieh&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Over-parameterization is commonly used to increase the expressivity of variational quantum circuits (VQCs), yet deeper and more highly parameterized circuits often exhibit poor trainability and limited generalization. In this work, we provide a theoretical explanation for this phenomenon from a function-class perspective. We show that sufficiently expressive, unstructured variational ansatze enter a Haar-like universality class in which both observable expectation values and parameter gradients concentrate exponentially with system size. As a consequence, the hypothesis class induced by such circuits collapses with high probability to a narrow family of near-constant functions, a phenomenon we term simplicity bias, with barren plateaus arising as a consequence rather than the root cause. Using tools from random matrix theory and concentration of measure, we rigorously characterize this universality class and establish uniform hypothesis-class collapse over finite datasets. We further show that this collapse is not unavoidable: tensor-structured VQCs, including tensor-network-based and tensor-hypernetwork parameterizations, lie outside the Haar-like universality class. By restricting the accessible unitary ensemble through bounded tensor rank or bond dimension, these architectures prevent concentration of measure, preserve output variability for local observables, and retain non-degenerate gradient signals even in over-parameterized regimes. Together, our results unify barren plateaus, expressivity limits, and generalization collapse under a single structural mechanism rooted in random-matrix universality, highlighting the central role of architectural inductive bias in variational quantum algorithms.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01877'&gt;arXiv:2601.01877&lt;/a&gt;] Published Mon, 05 Jan 2026 08:04:33 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01877</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 08:04:33 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>TT-FSI: Scalable Faithful Shapley Interactions via Tensor-Train</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01903</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Ungsik Kim, Suwon Lee&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; The Faithful Shapley Interaction (FSI) index uniquely satisfies the faithfulness axiom among Shapley interaction indices, but computing FSI requires $O(d^\ell \cdot 2^d)$ time and existing implementations use $O(4^d)$ memory. We present TT-FSI, which exploits FSI's algebraic structure via Matrix Product Operators (MPO). Our main theoretical contribution is proving that the linear operator $v \mapsto \text{FSI}(v)$ admits an MPO representation with TT-rank $O(\ell d)$, enabling an efficient sweep algorithm with $O(\ell^2 d^3 \cdot 2^d)$ time and $O(\ell d^2)$ core storage an exponential improvement over existing methods. Experiments on six datasets ($d=8$ to $d=20$) demonstrate up to 280$\times$ speedup over baseline, 85$\times$ over SHAP-IQ, and 290$\times$ memory reduction. TT-FSI scales to $d=20$ (1M coalitions) where all competing methods fail.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01903'&gt;arXiv:2601.01903&lt;/a&gt;] Published Mon, 05 Jan 2026 08:49:25 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01903</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 08:49:25 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Longitudinal-field fidelity susceptibility analysis of the $J_1$-$J_2$ transverse-field Ising model around $J_2/J_1 \approx 0.5$</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01893</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Yoshihiro Nishiyama&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; The square-lattice $J_1$-$J_2$ transverse-field (TF) Ising model was investigated with the exact diagonalization (ED) method. In order to analyze the TF-driven phase transition, we applied the longitudinal-field fidelity susceptibility $χ^{(h)}_F$, which is readily evaluated via the ED scheme. Here, the longitudinal field couples with the absolute value of the magnetic moment $|M|$ rather than the raw $M$ so that the remedied fidelity susceptibility exhibits a peak around the critical point; note that the spontaneous magnetization does not appear for the finite-size systems. As a preliminary survey, the modified fidelity susceptibility $χ^{(h)}_F$ is applied to the analysis of criticality for $J_2=0$, where a number of preceding results are available. Thereby, properly scaling the distance from the multi-criticality, $η=0.5-J_2$, the $χ^{(h)}_F$ data were cast into the crossover-scaling formula, and the multi-critical exponent for $χ_F^{(h)}$ is estimated. The result is cross-checked by the numerically evaluated $β$-function behavior.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01893'&gt;arXiv:2601.01893&lt;/a&gt;] Published Mon, 05 Jan 2026 08:36:02 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01893</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 08:36:02 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge disproportionation as a possible mechanism towards polar antiferromagnetic metal in molecular orbital crystal</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02048</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Yang Shen, Shuai Qu, Gang Li, Pu Yu, Guang-Ming Zhang&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Polar antiferromagnetic metals have recently garnered increasing interests due to their combined traits of both ferromagnets and antiferromagnets for spintronic applications. However, the inherently incompatible nature of antiferromagnet, metallicity and polarity pose a significant challenge. We propose that charge disproportionation can lead to this novel state in negative charge transfer gap regime in molecular orbital crystal by molecular orbital analyses of first-principles DFT+$U$ electronic band structure for representative Ruddlesden-Popper bilayer perovskite oxides Sr$_3$Co$_2$O$_7$, corroborated by Density Matrix Renormalization Group calculation. Due to the negative charge transfer nature of Co$^{4+}$ and imposed by strong interlayer coupling, localized molecular orbitals stemming from the hybridization of Co $d_{z^2}$ and $d_{xz/yz}$ orbitals through the apical oxygen $p$ orbitals are preferably emergent within each bilayer unit, which develop antiferromagnetic ordering by invoking Hubbard repulsion. Charge disproportionation driven by Hund's physics, makes an occupation imbalance with broken inversion symmetry in the remaining $d_{xy}$ and $d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbitals from distinct Co atoms within the bilayer unit, resulting in the polar metallicity. Meanwhile, this charge disproportionation scenario allows consequent conducting carriers to couple with interlayer local spins via Hund's coupling, giving rise to in-plane double-exchange ferromagnetism. Our molecular orbital formulation further provides a guide towards an effective Hamiltonian for modelling the unconventional synergy of metallicity, polarity and antiferromagnetism in Sr$_3$Co$_2$O$_7$, which may be a unified framework widely applicable to double-layer Ruddlesden-Popper perovskite oxides.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02048'&gt;arXiv:2601.02048&lt;/a&gt;] Published Mon, 05 Jan 2026 12:07:38 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02048</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 12:07:38 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Calculation of the Maximal Rényi Divergence for a Matrix Product State via Generalized Eigenvalue Density Matrix Renormalization Group</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02122</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Uri Levin, Noa Feldman, Moshe Goldstein&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; The study of quantum and classical correlations between subsystems is fundamental to understanding many-body physics. In quantum information theory, the quantum mutual information, $I(A;B)$, is a measure of correlation between the subsystems $A,B$ in a quantum state, and is defined by the means of the von Neumann entropy: $I\left(A;B\right)=S\left(ρ_{A}\right)+S\left(ρ_{B}\right)-S\left(ρ_{AB}\right)$. However, such a computation requires an exponential amount of resources. This is a defining feature of quantum systems, the infamous ``curse of dimensionality'' . Other measures, which are based on Rényi divergences instead of von Neumann entropy, were suggested as alternatives in a recent paper showing them to possess important theoretical features, and making them leading candidates as mutual information measures. In this work, we concentrate on the maximal Rényi divergence. This measure can be shown to be the solution of a generalized eigenvalue problem. To calculate it efficiently for a 1D state represented as a matrix product state, we develop a generalized eigenvalue version of the density matrix renormalization group algorithm. We benchmark our method for the paradigmatic XXZ chain, and show that the maximal Rényi divergence may exhibit different trends than the von Neumann mutual information.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02122'&gt;arXiv:2601.02122&lt;/a&gt;] Published Mon, 05 Jan 2026 13:54:16 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02122</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 13:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum dynamics of cosmological particle production: interacting quantum field theories with matrix product states</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02331</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Evan Budd, Adrien Florio, David Frenklakh, Swagato Mukherjee&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding real-time dynamics of interacting quantum fields in curved spacetime remains a major theoretical challenge. We employ tensor network methods to study such dynamics using interacting scalar and gauge theories in 1+1 spacetime dimensions, subject to a quench modeling a homogeneously expanding gravitational background. The models considered are the scalar $λφ^4$ theory and the Schwinger model, i.e. a Dirac fermion coupled to a $U(1)$ gauge field which is equivalent via bosonization to a scalar field with a cosine self-interaction. In the free scalar limit, both theories reproduce known analytical results, providing a nontrivial numerical validation of bosonization in curved spacetime for the Schwinger model. Our central finding is that self-interactions lead to a suppression of gravitational particle production compared to the free-field case, as evidenced by two-point functions and the spectra of produced particles. We further examine the behavior of entanglement generation and find that interactions suppress entanglement growth in the $λφ^4$ theory, while in the Schwinger model, the interplay between suppressed particle production and enhanced inter-particle correlations leads to more complex entanglement behavior. Our results pave the way for further explorations of nonperturbative quantum real-time dynamics of interacting scalar and gauge theories in arbitrary gravitational backgrounds.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02331'&gt;arXiv:2601.02331&lt;/a&gt;] Published Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:23:52 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02331</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:23:52 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor renormalization group approach to critical phenomena via symmetry-twisted partition functions</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02681</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Shinichiro Akiyama, Raghav G. Jha, Jun Maeda, Yuya Tanizaki, Judah Unmuth-Yockey&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; The locality of field theories strongly constrains the possible behaviors of symmetry-twisted partition functions, and thus they serve as order parameters to detect low-energy realizations of global symmetries, such as spontaneous symmetry breaking (SSB). We demonstrate that the tensor renormalization group (TRG) offers an efficient framework to compute the symmetry-twisted partition functions, which enables us to detect the symmetry-breaking transition and also to study associated critical phenomena. As concrete examples of SSB, we investigate the two-dimensional (2D) classical Ising model and the three-dimensional (3D) classical $O(2)$ nonlinear sigma model, and we identify their critical points solely from the twisted partition function. By employing the finite-size scaling argument, we find the critical temperature $T_c=2.2017(2)$ with the critical exponent $ν= 0.663(33)$ for the 3D $O(2)$ model. In addition, we also study the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless (BKT) criticality of the 2D classical $O(2)$ model by extracting the helicity modulus from the twisted partition functions, and we obtain the BKT transition temperature, $T_{\mathrm{BKT}}=0.8928(2)$.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02681'&gt;arXiv:2601.02681&lt;/a&gt;] Published Tue, 06 Jan 2026 03:27:16 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02681</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 03:27:16 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic freedom, lost: Complex conformal field theory in the two-dimensional $O(N&gt;2)$ nonlinear sigma model and its realization in the spin-1 Heisenberg chain</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02459</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Christopher Yang, Thomas Scaffidi&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; The two-dimensional $O(N)$ nonlinear sigma model (NLSM) is asymptotically free for $N&gt;2$: it exhibits neither a nontrivial fixed point nor spontaneous symmetry-breaking. Here we show that a nontrivial fixed point generically does exist in the $\textit{complex}$ coupling plane and is described by a complex conformal field theory (CCFT). This CCFT fixed point is generic in the sense that it has a single relevant singlet operator, and is thus expected to arise in any non-Hermitian model with $O(N)$ symmetry upon tuning a single complex parameter. We confirm this prediction numerically by locating the CCFT at $N = 3$ in a non-Hermitian spin-1 antiferromagnetic Heisenberg chain, finding good agreement between the complex central charge and scaling dimensions and those obtained by analytic continuation of real fixed points from $N\leq 2$. We further construct a realistic Lindbladian for a spin-1 chain whose no-click dynamics are governed by the non-Hermitian Hamiltonian realizing the CCFT. Since the CCFT vacuum is the eigenstate with the smallest decay rate, the system naturally relaxes under dissipative dynamics toward a CFT state, thus providing a route to preparing long-range entangled states through engineered dissipation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02459'&gt;arXiv:2601.02459&lt;/a&gt;] Published Mon, 05 Jan 2026 19:00:00 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02459</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Who can compete with quantum computers? Lecture notes on quantum inspired tensor networks computational techniques</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03035</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Xavier Waintal, Chen-How Huang, Christoph W. Groth&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; This is a set of lectures on tensor networks with a strong emphasis on the core algorithms involving Matrix Product States (MPS) and Matrix Product Operators (MPO). Compared to other presentations, particular care has been given to disentangle aspects of tensor networks from the quantum many-body problem: MPO/MPS algorithms are presented as a way to deal with linear algebra on extremely (exponentially) large matrices and vectors, regardless of any particular application. The lectures include well-known algorithms to find eigenvectors of MPOs (the celebrated DMRG), solve linear problems, and recent learning algorithms that allow one to map a known function into an MPS (the Tensor Cross Interpolation, or TCI, algorithm). The lectures end with a discussion of how to represent functions and perform calculus with tensor networks using the "quantics" representation. They include the detailed analytical construction of important MPOs such as those for differentiation, indefinite integration, convolution, and the quantum Fourier transform. Three concrete applications are discussed in detail: the simulation of a quantum computer (either exactly or with compression), the simulation of a quantum annealer, and techniques to solve partial differential equations (e.g. Poisson, diffusion, or Gross-Pitaevskii) within the "quantics" representation. The lectures have been designed to be accessible to a first-year PhD student and include detailed proofs of all statements.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03035'&gt;arXiv:2601.03035&lt;/a&gt;] Published Tue, 06 Jan 2026 14:09:10 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03035</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 14:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Unknown</dc:creator></item>
  </channel>
</rss>