<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:ns0="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>DMRG cond-mat</title>
    <link>http://quattro.phys.sci.kobe-u.ac.jp/dmrg/condmat.html</link>
    <description>Aggregated feed from DMRG cond-mat page, includes abstracts and authors from arXiv (sorted by publication date, newest first)</description>
    <ns0:link href="http://quattro.phys.sci.kobe-u.ac.jp/dmrg/condmat.html" rel="self" />
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 01:37:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-Dirac spin liquids and frustrated quantum magnetism on the trellis lattice</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02663</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Sourin Chatterjee, Atanu Maity, Janik Potten, Tobias Müller, Andreas Feuerpfeil, Ronny Thomale, Karlo Penc, Harald O. Jeschke, Rhine Samajdar, Yasir Iqbal&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Geometrical frustration in quantum magnets provides a fertile setting for unconventional phases of matter, including quantum spin liquids (QSLs). The trellis lattice, with its complex site arrangements and edge-sharing triangular motifs, presents a promising platform for such physics. In this work, we undertake a comprehensive classification of all fully symmetric QSLs on the trellis lattice using the projective symmetry group approach within the Abrikosov fermion representation. We find 7 U(1) and 25 $\mathbb{Z}_{2}$ short-ranged $\textit{Ans\"atze}$, uncovering both gapped and Dirac QSLs as well as a novel semi-Dirac spin liquid, in which the spinon dispersion is linear along one momentum direction but quadratic along the orthogonal one. We demonstrate that such dispersions can occur only at high-symmetry points in the Brillouin zone with $C_{2v}$ little groups and analyze their characteristic correlation signatures. Moreover, by optimizing over all mean-field states, we map out a phase diagram -- featuring six distinct phases -- of the nearest-neighbor Heisenberg Hamiltonian on the trellis lattice. Going beyond mean field, we also assess equal-time and dynamical spin structure factors of these phases using density-matrix renormalization group and Keldysh pseudofermion functional renormalization group calculations. Finally, we identify four cuprate and vanadate compounds as promising experimental realizations and provide spectroscopic predictions, based on first-principles Hamiltonians, as a guide for future neutron-scattering studies on these materials.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02663'&gt;arXiv:2509.02663&lt;/a&gt;] Published Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:00:00 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02663</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Sourin Chatterjee, Atanu Maity, Janik Potten, Tobias Müller, Andreas Feuerpfeil, Ronny Thomale, Karlo Penc, Harald O. Jeschke, Rhine Samajdar, Yasir Iqbal</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Doping a spin-one Mott insulator: possible application to bilayer nickelate</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02673</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Hanbit Oh, Hui Yang, Ya-Hui Zhang&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; In this article, we review some recent theoretical developments on potential high-temperature superconductors and unconventional metallic states that can arise from doping a spin-one Mott insulator in the $d^{8}$ valence. These studies are particularly relevant-though not limited-to the recently discovered bilayer nickelate superconductor La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$. We focus on a ferromagnetic (FM) Kondo lattice model with mobile electrons in the $d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbital coupled to the localized spin moments in $d_{z^2}$ orbital through a large Hund's coupling $J_H$. In the large $J_H$ limit, the model reduces to the type II t-J model with a mixture of spin-half singlon states and spin-one doublon states. We summarize DMRG results on the Luther-Emery liquid in one dimensional chain and two-leg ladder. Then we mainly focus on bilayer square lattice and show that a large inter-layer coupling $J_\perp$ of $d_{z^2}$ orbital can induce strong inter-layer pairing of $d_{x^2-y^2}$ orbital. In the strong $J_\perp$ limit, a kinetic-energy driven high $T_c$ superconductivity is demonstrated in an ideal model with only a single hopping term. Furthermore, the model predicts a symmetric pseudogap metal-dubbed `second Fermi liquid"-in the underdoped regime, yielding a phase diagram analogous to that of hole-doped cuprates. The bilayer Kondo model therefore, presents a promising platform for both realizing higher-Tc superconductors and exploring non-Fermi liquid physics. We also comment on the possible limitations of the current models for the bilayer nickelate material and point out some future directions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02673'&gt;arXiv:2509.02673&lt;/a&gt;] Published Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:00:01 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02673</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Hanbit Oh, Hui Yang, Ya-Hui Zhang</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust superconductivity upon doping chiral spin liquid and Chern insulators in a Hubbard-Hofstadter model</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02675</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Clemens Kuhlenkamp, Stefan Divic, Michael P. Zaletel, Tomohiro Soejima, Ashvin Vishwanath&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Demonstrating superconductivity in purely repulsive Hubbard models is a compelling goal which underscores the counter-intuitive ability of Coulomb interactions to mediate superconductivity. Here, we present numerical evidence for robust superconductivity in a triangular Hubbard-Hofstadter model at $\pi/2$ flux per plaquette. Employing infinite density matrix renormalization group calculations on infinite cylinders of finite circumference, we observe superconducting ground states for a wide range of dopings, whose pair-correlations strengthen as the 2D limit is approached. At a density of one electron per site, Hubbard interactions have been reported to drive the insulating parent state of the superconductor from an integer quantum Hall (IQH) state to a chiral spin liquid (CSL). Our findings give credence to a recent proposal that proximity to the IQH-CSL transition serves to make chiral superconductivity energetically favorable on doping, and also correctly predicts the nature of the edge modes in the superconductor. On the CSL side, this suggests the superconductor can be thought of as arising from Laughlin's `anyon superconductivity' mechanism. Thus the Hubbard-Hofstadter model studied here offers a clean and experimentally accessible setup, potentially realizable in moir\'e heterostructures, for exploring the properties of anyonic matter at finite density and the interplay of topological order, quantum criticality and superconductivity.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02675'&gt;arXiv:2509.02675&lt;/a&gt;] Published Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:00:01 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02675</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Clemens Kuhlenkamp, Stefan Divic, Michael P. Zaletel, Tomohiro Soejima, Ashvin Vishwanath</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering and induced false vacuum decay in the two-dimensional quantum Ising model</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02702</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Luka Pavešić, Marco Di Liberto, Simone Montangero&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; We study scattering in the quantum Ising model in two dimensions. In the ordered phase, the spectrum contains a ladder of bound states and intertwined scattering resonances, which enable various scattering channels. By preparing wave packets on a $24 \times 24$ lattice and evolving the state with tensor networks, we explore and characterize these regimes, ranging from elastic scattering in the perturbative regime, to non-perturbative processes closer to the critical point. Then, we break the spin inversion symmetry and study the stability of the metastable false vacuum state on the collision of its excitations. We find that a highly-energetic scattering process can induce a violent decay of the false vacuum, and investigate the spread of the resulting true vacuum bubble.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02702'&gt;arXiv:2509.02702&lt;/a&gt;] Published Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:02:51 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02702</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:02:51 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Luka Pavešić, Marco Di Liberto, Simone Montangero</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Chiral Superconductivity in the Triangular-Lattice Hofstadter-Hubbard Model</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02757</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Feng Chen, Wen O. Wang, Jia-Xin Zhang, Leon Balents, D. N. Sheng&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Moir\'e materials provide exciting platforms for studying the interplay of strong electronic correlation and large magnetic flux effects. We study the lightly doped Hofstadter-Hubbard model on a triangular lattice through large-scale density matrix renormalization group and determinantal quantum Monte Carlo simulations. We find strong evidence for a robust chiral superconducting (SC) phase with dominant power-law pairing correlations and a quantized spin Chern number. The SC phase emerges at very weak interaction and grows stronger at intermediate interaction strengths (U ) for a wide range of hole doping. We also discuss the possible distinct nature of the normal state in different U regimes. Our work provides theoretical insights into the emergence of topological superconductivity from doping topological Chern bands or magnetic flux induced chiral spin liquid states of Moir\'e materials.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02757'&gt;arXiv:2509.02757&lt;/a&gt;] Published Tue, 02 Sep 2025 19:04:03 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02757</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 19:04:03 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Feng Chen, Wen O. Wang, Jia-Xin Zhang, Leon Balents, D. N. Sheng</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Deconfined Quantum Critical Point in Quantum Hall Bilayers</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03079</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Guangyu Yu, Tao Xiang, Zheng Zhu&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Deconfined quantum critical points (DQCPs) represent an unconventional class of quantum criticality beyond the Landau-Ginzburg-Wilson-Fisher paradigm. Nevertheless, both their theoretical identification and experimental realization remain challenging. Here we report compelling evidence of a DQCP in quantum Hall bilayers with half-filled $n=2$ Landau levels in each layer, based on large-scale variational uniform matrix product state (VUMPS) simulations and exact diagonalization (ED). By systematically analyzing the ground-state fidelity, low-lying energy spectra, exciton superfluid and stripe order parameters, and ground-state energy derivatives, we identify a direct and continuous quantum phase transition between two distinct symmetry-breaking phases by tuning the layer separation: an exciton superfluid phase with spontaneous $U(1)$ symmetry breaking at small separation, and a unidirectional charge density wave with broken translational symmetry at large separation. Our results highlight quantum Hall bilayers as an ideal platform for realizing and experimentally probing DQCPs under precisely tunable interactions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03079'&gt;arXiv:2509.03079&lt;/a&gt;] Published Wed, 03 Sep 2025 07:18:11 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03079</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 07:18:11 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Guangyu Yu, Tao Xiang, Zheng Zhu</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>TeRA: Vector-based Random Tensor Network for High-Rank Adaptation of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03234</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Yuxuan Gu, Wuyang Zhou, Giorgos Iacovides, Danilo Mandic&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) methods, such as Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA), have significantly reduced the number of trainable parameters needed in fine-tuning large language models (LLMs). Subsequent developments of LoRA-style adapters have diverged into two main directions: (1) enhancing model expressivity with high-rank adapters, and (2) pushing for further parameter reduction, as exemplified by vector-based methods. However, these approaches present a trade-off, as achieving the expressivity of high-rank weight updates typically comes at the cost of sacrificing the extreme parameter efficiency offered by vector-based techniques. To address this issue, we propose a vector-based random \underline{\textbf{Te}}nsor network for high-\underline{\textbf{R}}ank \underline{\textbf{A}}daptation (TeRA), a novel PEFT method that achieves high-rank weight updates while retaining the parameter efficiency of vector-based PEFT adapters. This is achieved by parameterizing the tensorized weight update matrix as a Tucker-like tensor network (TN), in which large randomly initialized factors are frozen and shared across layers, while only small layer-specific scaling vectors, formed by entries in diagonal factor matrices, are trained. This design effectively decouples the rank of the weight update matrix from the number of trainable parameters. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that TeRA matches or even outperforms high-rank adapters, while requiring a trainable parameter count similar to vector-based methods. Theoretical analysis and ablation studies further validate the effectiveness of our approach.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03234'&gt;arXiv:2509.03234&lt;/a&gt;] Published Wed, 03 Sep 2025 11:46:24 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03234</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 11:46:24 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Yuxuan Gu, Wuyang Zhou, Giorgos Iacovides, Danilo Mandic</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology meets superconductivity in a one-dimensional $t-J$ model of magnetic atoms</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03387</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Leonardo Bellinato Giacomelli, Thomas Bland, Louis Lafforgue, Francesca Ferlaino, Manfred J. Mark, Luca Barbiero&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Strongly interacting fermions represent the key constituent of several intriguing phases of matter. However, due to the inherent complexity of these systems, important regimes are still inaccessible. Here, we derive a realistic and flexible setup based on ultracold magnetic lanthanide atoms trapped in a one-dimensional optical lattice. Leveraging their large magnetic moments, we design a fermionic $t-J$ model with independently tunable hopping, spin-spin couplings, and onsite interaction. Through combined analytical and numerical analysis, we uncover a variety of many-body quantum phases$-$including superconducting and topological states. Crucially, in the regime of attractive onsite interaction we reveal that topology and superconductivity coexist, thus giving rise to an exotic state of matter: a topological triplet superconductor. We also outline a practical protocol to prepare and detect all discovered phases using current experimental techniques. Our results establish an alternative and powerful route for a deeper understanding of strongly interacting fermionic quantum matter.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03387'&gt;arXiv:2509.03387&lt;/a&gt;] Published Wed, 03 Sep 2025 15:05:11 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03387</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 15:05:11 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Leonardo Bellinato Giacomelli, Thomas Bland, Louis Lafforgue, Francesca Ferlaino, Manfred J. Mark, Luca Barbiero</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal representation of the long-range entanglement in the family of Toric Code states</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03422</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Mohammad Hossein Zarei, Mohsen Rahmani Haghighi&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Since the long range entanglement is a universal characteristic of topological quantum states belonging to the same class, a suitable mathematical representation of the long range entanglement has to be also universal. In this Letter, we introduce such a representation for the family of Toric Code states by using Kitaev's Ladders as building blocks. We consider Toric Code states corresponding to various planar graphs and apply non-local dientanglers to qubits corresponding to non-contractible cycles that satisfy a topological constraint. We demonstrate that, independent of the geometry of the underlying graph, disentanglers convert Toric Code states into a tensor product of Kitaev's Ladder states. Since Kitaev's Ladders with arbitrary geometric configurations include the short-range entanglements, we conclude that the above universal and non-local pattern of entanglement between ladders is responsible of the long-range entanglement inherent in Toric Code states. Our result emphasizes in the capability of such non-local representations to describe topological order in ground-state wave functions of topological quantum systems.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03422'&gt;arXiv:2509.03422&lt;/a&gt;] Published Wed, 03 Sep 2025 15:49:57 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03422</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 15:49:57 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Mohammad Hossein Zarei, Mohsen Rahmani Haghighi</dc:creator></item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipationless dynamics of spin supersolid states in a spin-1/2 triangular antiferromagnet with impurities</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03489</link>
      <description>&lt;b&gt;Author(s):&lt;/b&gt; Yixuan Huang, Yuan Gao, Wei Li, Seiji Yunoki, Sadamichi Maekawa&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;Abstract:&lt;/b&gt; Motivated by recent experimental observations of possible spin supersolid states in triangular lattice compounds, we study the dynamical properties of various ground states in the spin-1/2 easy-axis antiferromagnetic Heisenberg model with impurities under magnetic fields, using numerical Density Matrix Renormalization Group methods. For both spin supersolid states in the low and high fields, the gapless Goldstone mode at the $K$ points remains robust with impurities, which is related to the presence of spin superfluidity. As a comparison, we find a splitting of magnon band at the same impurity density level in the conventional magnetic state, the so-called up-up-down state. In addition, the finite superfluid stiffness probed by the twisted phase in the spin supersolid states is consistent with the excitation spectrum. We argue that this excitation spectrum with impurity provides direct evidence of the dissipationless dynamics in the spin supersolid states, which could be tested in neutron scattering experiments.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;b&gt;[&lt;a href='http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03489'&gt;arXiv:2509.03489&lt;/a&gt;] Published Wed, 03 Sep 2025 17:18:04 UTC&lt;/b&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03489</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 17:18:04 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>Yixuan Huang, Yuan Gao, Wei Li, Seiji Yunoki, Sadamichi Maekawa</dc:creator></item>
  </channel>
</rss>